A Guide to the First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.) records, 1714-2002
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.) records, 1714-2002
Library of Virginia
51098
1.5 cubic feet (4 boxes).
First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased
Historical Information
The "First Baptist Church" of Richmond was established in 1780 comprised of both White and African American members. In 1841, the White members spit from the congregation to from a separate church at 12th & Broad, and the African American congregation would come to be known as "First African Baptist Church" of Richmond.
Scope and Content
Church Records,1714 - 2002, of The First Baptist Church of Richmond, Virginia. The collection includes records from both the First Baptist Church and First African Baptist Church comprised of bulletins, correspondence, financial records, letters, newspaper clippings, and photos. The records detail the history and organization of the churches.
Contents List
- Church administration (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1838-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- History (Box 1, Folder 3)
- List of prayers and sermons (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photographs--Leslie Watson, organist; Dr. William Tolbert; John Mosely's birthday; Groundbreaking ceremonies (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photographs--people (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs of First Baptist Church and First African Baptist Church, ca. 1870-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photographs of First Baptist Church (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photographic negatives of First Baptist Church (Box 1, Folder 9)
- General papers, 1874-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial records--pew certificates; estimate of cost; Every Member Canvas; Trustees of First Baptist Church; Woman's Missionary Society; Baraca Boys Fund; tentative budget, 1846-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Events and services, 1859-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Integration lawsuits, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Integration lawsuits, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Newspaper articles about integration at First Baptist Church (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Paul E. Crandall papers (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Whitmell S. Forbes papers (Box 2, Folder 7)
- William A. Huey correspondence, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- George W. McDaniel papers (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Luther Joe Thompson papers (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Newspaper articles (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 12)
- First Baptist Church offering envelopes, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- First Baptist Church offering envelopes, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- First Baptist Church offering envelopes, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- First Baptist Church offering envelopes, 1914-1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- First African Baptist Church papers, 1875-1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Account book--estate of Daisy B. Walden, 1910-1914 (Box 3)
- Robert Norden document (photocopy); Survey of property known as First Baptist Church; First Baptist Church first mortgage 4 1/2% real estate note, 1714, 1893, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- First African Baptist Church--photograph and Harper's article, ca. 1875 and undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Miniature map and enlarged map of Sheppard property (Box 4, Folder 2)